<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on CapFab.io</title>
    <link>http://capfab.io/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on CapFab.io</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 13:06:26 +0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://capfab.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Markov Decision Processes</title>
      <link>http://capfab.io/blog/markov-decision-processes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 13:06:26 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://capfab.io/blog/markov-decision-processes/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this blog post, we are going to talk about Markov Decision Processes (MDP). The format is a bit longer than the usual blog post. We will go into quite a bit of details about MDPs. Some mathematics will be involved.
MDPs are very important in the context of reinforcement learning (RL), because lots of RL problems can be put into some form or another as MDPs. For example, the bandit problem, which is a typical RL problem, is actually an MDP with one state.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dollar Cost Averaging: Does It Work ?</title>
      <link>http://capfab.io/blog/dollar-cost-averaging-does-it-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 13:06:26 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://capfab.io/blog/dollar-cost-averaging-does-it-work/</guid>
      <description>Introduction There is a lot of people on the internet that say that instead of putting all of your money at once in the market, you should instead divide that lump sum over a certain period of time with equal installments. The underlying logic is that if the market falls after you&#39;ve invested a lump-sum, it will be devastating. Instead the dollar cost strategy avoids such tragic event by not investing everything at once and instead spread your bets at different moments through time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GameStop: A Paradigm Shift In Finance?</title>
      <link>http://capfab.io/blog/gamestop-a-paradigm-shift-in-finance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 13:06:26 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://capfab.io/blog/gamestop-a-paradigm-shift-in-finance/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this blog post, we are going to talk about what has been happening to GameStop (with symbol share GME) and how a group in reddit has been able to push the valuation of GME by more than 1400% (r/wallstreetbets) in the first month of 2021. Moreover, Robinhood, an app that is heavily used by retail investors, decided that they wouldn&#39;t allow their users to buy more shares of GME on Thursday (28 Jan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Bitcoin Worthless ?</title>
      <link>http://capfab.io/blog/biggest-risk-to-bitcoin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:06:26 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://capfab.io/blog/biggest-risk-to-bitcoin/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this blog post, we are going to address one of the biggest security problems of cryptocurrencies: quantum computers. The value of the bitcoin is sustained by the fact that people trust the transaction process between two entities and secured in the blockchain. Basically, they trust the fact that their bitcoins couldn&#39;t be stolen easily. That isn&#39;t true anymore if a person/entity has access to a big quantum computer. In order to understand why, we need to present some fundamentals of cryptography.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Portfolio For Lazy Investors</title>
      <link>http://capfab.io/blog/portfolio-for-lazy-investors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:06:26 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://capfab.io/blog/portfolio-for-lazy-investors/</guid>
      <description>Introduction One of the topics that is of main interest to me and (I believe) to lots of investors is: how to get the same returns on a certain portfolio, while lowering the risk. This is a difficult question that has a simple answer for investors that do not want to waste too much time on it: the answer is risk parity.
What is risk parity ? There are different sorts of investors: the ones that like to take more risks than the market in exchange of a higher premium and the ones that are risk averse and prefer steady returns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algo Trading: The Optimal Execution Problem</title>
      <link>http://capfab.io/blog/optimal-execution-in-algo-trading/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 23:06:26 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://capfab.io/blog/optimal-execution-in-algo-trading/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Algorithmic trading is omnipresent in the financial industry, where a form of automated trading executes the orders and decides the amount of shares, the entry point and/or the exit point. In the present blog post, we define and explore the problem of optimal execution in the context of algorithmic trading.
Optimal Execution Let&#39;s imagine that you need to sell a large amount of shares $S_t$ at a certain time $t$ with $P_t$.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>