<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on CapFab.io</title>
    <link>http://capfab.io/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on CapFab.io</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:06:26 +0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://capfab.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Bitcoin Worthless ?</title>
      <link>http://capfab.io/blog/biggest-risk-to-bitcoin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:06:26 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://capfab.io/blog/biggest-risk-to-bitcoin/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this blog post, we are going to address one of the biggest security problems of cryptocurrencies: quantum computers. The value of the bitcoin is sustained by the fact that people trust the transaction process between two entities and secured in the blockchain. Basically, they trust the fact that their bitcoins couldn&#39;t be stolen easily. That isn&#39;t true anymore if a person/entity has access to a big quantum computer. In order to understand why, we need to present some fundamentals of cryptography.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Portfolio For Lazy Investors</title>
      <link>http://capfab.io/blog/portfolio-for-lazy-investors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:06:26 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://capfab.io/blog/portfolio-for-lazy-investors/</guid>
      <description>Introduction One of the topics that is of main interest to me and (I believe) to lots of investors is: how to get the same returns on a certain portfolio, while lowering the risk. This is a difficult question that has a simple answer for investors that do not want to waste too much time on it: the answer is risk parity.
What is risk parity ? There are different sorts of investors: the ones that like to take more risks than the market in exchange of a higher premium and the ones that are risk averse and prefer steady returns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algo Trading: The Optimal Execution Problem</title>
      <link>http://capfab.io/blog/optimal-execution-in-algo-trading/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 23:06:26 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://capfab.io/blog/optimal-execution-in-algo-trading/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Algorithmic trading is omnipresent in the financial industry, where a form of automated trading executes the orders and decides the amount of shares, the entry point and/or the exit point. In the present blog post, we define and explore the problem of optimal execution in the context of algorithmic trading.
Optimal Execution Let&#39;s imagine that you need to sell a large amount of shares $S_t$ at a certain time $t$ with $P_t$.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>